Now, I'm an ethnobotanist.
我是名民族植物学家。
That's a scientist who  works in the rainforest
我在热带雨林工作，
to document how people use local plants.
记录人们如何使用当地植物。
I've been doing this for a long time,
我做这项工作很久了，
and I want to tell you,
我可以告诉大家，
these people know these forests and these medicinal treasures
这些人对当地森林和里面医药珍宝的了解
better than we do and better than we ever will.
比我们多得多，永远多得多。
But also, these cultures,
但是，这些文化，
these indigenous cultures,
这些土著文化，
are disappearing much faster than the forests themselves.
消失得比森林还快。
And the greatest and most endangered species
在亚马逊热带雨林中，
in the Amazon Rainforest is not the jaguar,
最伟大而最濒危的物种不是美洲豹，
it's not the harpy eagle,
也不是美洲角雕，
it's the isolated and uncontacted tribes.
而是与世隔绝的人类部落。
Now four years ago, I injured my  foot in a climbing accident
四年前，我在爬山时伤了脚，
and I went to the doctor.
我去看医生。
She gave me heat,
她给我进行热疗，
she gave me cold, aspirin,
进行冰疗，用阿司匹林，
narcotic painkillers, anti-inflammatories,
用麻醉止痛剂，抗炎药，
cortisone shots.
注射可的松。
It didn't work.
没有疗效。
Several months later,
几个月后，
I was in the northeast Amazon,
我在亚马逊东北部，
walked into a village,
我走进一个村落，
and the shaman said, "You're limping."
萨满说，“你跛了。”
And I'll never forget this as long as I live.
这一幕我一生都不会忘记。
He looked me in the face and he said,
他看着我的脸，对我说，
"Take off your shoe and give  me your machete."
“脱鞋，把你的砍刀给我。”
(Laughter)
（笑声）
He walked over to a palm tree
他走向一棵棕榈树，
and carved off a fern,
切下来一片蕨，
threw it in the fire,
扔到火里，
applied it to my foot,
然后敷在我脚上，
threw it in a pot of water,
然后又扔进了一壶水中，
and had me drink the tea.
让我把那个当茶喝了。
The pain disappeared for seven months.
整整七个月，我再也没疼过。
When it came back, I went to see the shaman again.
复发后，我又去见萨满。
He gave me the same treatment,
他对我进行同样的疗法，
and I've been cured for three years now.
现在我已经痊愈三年了。
Who would you rather be treated by?
你想让谁给你治病？
(Applause)
（鼓掌）
Now, make no mistake — Western medicine
别误会 — 西医
is the most successful system of healing ever devised,
是人类发明的最成功的医疗体系，
but there's plenty of holes in it.
但它也有缺陷。
Where's the cure for breast cancer?
乳腺癌的疗法在哪里？
Where's the cure for schizophrenia?
神经分裂症的疗法在哪里？
Where's the cure for acid reflux?
胃酸倒流的疗法在哪里？
Where's the cure for insomnia?
失眠症的疗法在哪里？
The fact is that these people
事实是，这些土著人
can sometimes, sometimes, sometimes cure things we cannot.
在有些时候，能治疗我们治不了的病。
Here you see a medicine man in the northeast Amazon
这是一位亚马逊东北部的药师
treating leishmaniasis,
在治疗利什曼病。
a really nasty protozoal disease
利什曼病是一种非常恶心的原虫疾病，
that afflicts 12 million people around the world.
全世界超过一千两百万人受其困扰。
Western treatment are injections of antimony.
西医的疗法是进行锑注射。
They're painful, they're expensive,
这种疗法让人很痛苦，也很昂贵，
and they're probably not good for your heart;
而且这种疗法对病人的心脏也可能有副作用。
it's a heavy metal.
锑是重金属。
This man cures it with three plants from the Amazon Rainforest.
这名药师能用三种亚马逊雨林的草药来进行治疗。
This is the magic frog.
这个是魔蛙。
My colleague, the late great Loren McIntyre,
我已故的同事洛伦·麦金太尔，
discoverer of the source  lake of the Amazon,
他发现了亚马逊的河源湖，
Laguna McIntyre in the Peruvian Andes,
秘鲁安第斯的麦金太尔湖，
was lost on the Peru-Brazil border about 30 years ago.
他30年前在秘鲁巴西边境迷路了。
He was rescued by a group of  isolated Indians called the Matsés.
他被一群叫做Matsés的与世隔绝的印第安人救了下来。
They beckoned for him to follow them into the forest, which he did.
他们示意他跟随他们进入丛林，他照做了。
There, they took out palm leaf baskets.
在那里，他们拿出了棕榈树叶筐，
There, they took out these green monkey frogs —
里面他们拿出了这种绿色的猴蛙 —
these are big suckers, they're like this —
个头都是大家伙，有这么 —
and they began licking them.
然后他们开始舔这种蛙。
It turns out, they're highly hallucinogenic.
这种蛙有高度的致幻作用。
McIntyre wrote about this and it was read  by the editor of High Times magazine.
麦金太尔把这个写了出来，《鼎盛时期》杂志的编辑看了。
You see that ethnobotanists have  friends in all sorts of strange cultures.
从中你可以看出民族植物学家在各种奇怪的圈子都有朋友。
This guy decided he would go down to the Amazon and give it a whirl,
这名编辑决定自己去亚马逊爽一下，
or give it a lick, and  he did, and he wrote,
舔一下，他真这样做了，他写到，
"My blood pressure went through the roof,
“我的血压爆表了，
I lost full control of my bodily functions,
我对我的身体机能完全失去了控制。
I passed out in a heap,
我昏厥了，
I woke up in a hammock six hours later,
六个小时后我在一张吊床里醒来，
felt like God for two days."
两天内都觉得自己跟神仙似的。”
(Laughter)
（笑声）
An Italian chemist read this and said,
一位意大利化学家读后说，
"I'm not really interested in the theological  aspects of the green monkey frog.
“我对这种绿猴蛙魔幻的一面没太大兴趣，
What's this about the change in blood pressure?"
可这个血压变化是怎么回事？”
Now, this is an Italian chemist
现在，这名意大利化学家
who's working on a new treatment for high blood pressure
正在研究新的治疗高血压的方法，
based on peptides in the skin of the green monkey frog,
用的就是绿猴蛙皮肤中的肽，
and other scientists are looking at a cure for drug-resistant Staph aureus.
而其他科学家也正在研究用这个肽来治疗耐药性的金黄色葡萄球菌。
How ironic if these isolated  Indians and their magic frog
如果这些隔绝的印第安人和他们的魔蛙
prove to be one of the cures.
是答案的话，那该有多讽刺。
Here's an ayahuasca shaman in the northwest Amazon, in the middle of a yage ceremony.
这里是一位亚马逊西北部的死藤水萨满，在卡皮木仪式中。
I took him to Los Angeles to meet a foundation officer
我带他去洛杉矶见一位基金会工作人员，
looking for support for monies to protect their culture.
寻求资金来保护他们的文化。
This fellow looked at the medicine man, and he said,
这个工作人员看了看这位药师，说，
"You didn't go to  medical school, did you?"
“你没上过医学院吧？”
The shaman said, "No, I did not."
萨满回答，“没有。”
He said, "Well, then what can you know about healing?"
他说，“那么，对治病你能懂什么？”
The shaman looked at him and he said,
萨满看着他，说，
"You know what? If you have  an infection, go to a doctor.
“你知道么？如果你有感染，那你去看医生。
But many human afflictions are diseases  of the heart, the mind and the spirit.
但很多人类疾病是心灵，头脑，和灵魂的病。
Western medicine can't  touch those. I cure them."
西医治不了。我能。”
(Applause)
（掌声）
But all is not rosy in learning from nature about new medicines.
但是从自然中提炼新药物也并不是那么美好。
This is a viper from Brazil,
这是条巴西毒蛇，
the venom of which was studied at the Universidade de São Paulo here.
毒液经圣保罗大学研究，
It was later developed into ACE inhibitors.
后来发展成ACE抑制剂。
This is a frontline treatment for hypertension.
治疗高血压的尖端药物。
Hypertension causes over 10 percent of all deaths on the planet every day.
地球上人类每天超过10%的死亡是因为高血压。
This is a $4 billion industry
这是个价值40亿美元的行业，
based on venom from a Brazilian snake,
用的就是巴西蛇的毒液，
and the Brazilians did not get a nickel.
但巴西人却一分钱也没得到。
This is not an acceptable way of doing business.
这样的做法是不可接受的。
The rainforest has been called the  greatest expression of life on Earth.
热带雨林被称作地球上最伟大的生态体系。
There's a saying in Suriname that I dearly love:
苏里南有一句谚语我很喜欢：
"The rainforests hold answers to questions we have yet to ask."
“热带雨林中有我们还未知晓的问题的答案。”
But as you all know, it's rapidly disappearing.
但是正如大家都知道的，热带雨林正在快速消失。
Here in Brazil, in the Amazon, around the world.
在巴西是这样，在亚马逊是这样，在全世界也是。
I took this picture from a small plane
我从一架小飞机上拍了这张照片，
flying over the eastern border of the Xingu indigenous reserve
当时正在飞过Xingu土著保护区的东部边境，
in the state of Mato Grosso to the northwest of here.
是从马托格罗索州到这里的西北部。
The top half of the picture,
照片的上半部分，
you see where the Indians live.
你能看到是印第安人的居住地。
The line through the middle is the eastern border of the reserve.
中间的线 是保护区的东部边界。
Top half Indians, bottom half white guys.
上半部分印第安人，下半部分白人。
Top half wonder drugs,
上半部分是奇妙的医药，
bottom half just a bunch of skinny-ass cows.
下半部分就是一群脑残。
Top half carbon sequestered in the forest where it belongs,
上半部分碳被储存在他们所属的森林中，
bottom half carbon in the atmosphere
下半部分碳排放到大气中，
where it's driving climate change.
导致气候变化。
In fact, the number two cause of carbon being released into the atmosphere is forest destruction.
事实上，大气碳排放的第二个原因就是森林破坏。
But in talking about destruction,
说到破坏，
it's important to keep in mind
很重要的是要记得
that the Amazon is the mightiest landscape of all.
亚马逊是最神奇的景观。
It's a place of beauty and wonder.
壮丽的地方，神奇的地方。
The biggest anteater in the world
世界上最大的食蚁兽
lives in the rain forest,
就生活在热带雨林，
tips the scale at 90 pounds.
重达90磅。
The goliath bird-eating spider
巨型的捕鸟蛛，
is the world's largest spider.
世界上最大的蜘蛛，
It's found in the Amazon as well.
也是在亚马逊。
The harpy eagle wingspan is over seven feet.
美洲角雕翼展超过7英尺，
And the black cayman —
还有黑鳄鱼 —
these monsters can tip the scale at over half a ton.
这些巨兽体重超过半吨。
They're known to be man-eaters.
他们据称能食人。
The anaconda, the largest snake,
还有水蟒，最大的蛇类，
the capybara, the largest rodent.
水豚，最大的啮齿类。
A specimen from here in Brazil tipped the scale at 201 pounds.
巴西的一个标本重达201磅。
Let's visit where these creatures live,
让我们来看看这些生物的家园，
the northeast Amazon,
亚马逊东北部，
home to the Akuriyo tribe.
Akuriyo部落的所在地。
Uncontacted peoples hold a  mystical and iconic role
与世隔绝的部落在我们的想象中
in our imagination.
是神秘而有代表性的。
These are the people who  know nature best.
他们是最了解自然的人。
These are the people who truly live in total harmony with nature.
他们是真正与自然和谐相处的人。
By our standards, some would dismiss these people as primitive.
用我们的标准来看，有人会觉得他们原始。
"They don't know how to make fire,
“他们不会生火。
or they didn't when they were first contacted."
起码刚跟外界接触时，他们不会。”
But they know the forest far better than we do.
但他们对森林的了解远远多于我们。
The Akuriyos have 35 words for honey,
Akuriyos人有35种词汇形容蜂蜜，
and other Indians look up to them as being the true masters of the emerald realm.
其他印第安人将他们视为热带雨林中真正的大师。
Here you see the face of my friend Pohnay.
这是我的朋友博奈。
When I was a teenager rocking out to the Rolling Stones in my hometown of New Orleans,
当我还年轻，在家乡新奥尔良听滚石乐队的歌时，
Pohnay was a forest nomad
博奈就已经在森林游牧，
roaming the jungles of the northeast Amazon
漫步在亚马逊东北部的丛林中，
in a small band, looking for game,
和小群落一起，打猎，
looking for medicinal plants,
寻找草药，
looking for a wife, in other small nomadic bands.
从别的小游牧群落中寻找配偶。
But it's people like these that know things that we don't,
正是他们这种人有我们不知道的智慧，
and they have lots of  lessons to teach us.
他们有很多东西能教给我们。
However, if you go into most of the forests of the Amazon,
但是，如果你去亚马逊森林的大多数地方，
there are no indigenous peoples.
你见不到土著部落。
This is what you find:
你能看到的是，
rock carvings which indigenous peoples, uncontacted peoples, used to sharpen the edge of the stone axe.
与世隔绝的土著部落磨斧头时在石头上留下的痕迹。
These cultures that once danced,
这些曾经跳舞，
made love, sang to the gods,
繁衍，赞颂神明，
worshipped the forest,
崇拜森林的群落，
all that's left is an imprint in stone, as you see here.
现在只留在岩石的痕迹中，就像这张图里的这样。
Let's move to the western Amazon,
我们再去看看西亚马逊，
which is really the epicenter of isolated peoples.
那里是与世隔绝的部落的中心。
Each of these dots represents
这里每一个点都代表着
a small, uncontacted tribe,
一个小的，未曾联系过的部落，
and the big reveal today is we believe there are 14 or 15 isolated groups in the Colombian Amazon alone.
现在我们认为单单在哥伦比亚亚马逊就有14或15个隔绝部落。
Why are these people isolated?
为什么这些人与世隔绝？
They know we exist, they know there's an outside world.
他们知道我们存在，他们知道有外界世界。
This is a form of resistance.
这是一种反抗。
They have chosen to remain isolated,
他们选择保持隔绝，
and I think it is their human right to remain so.
我觉得他们有权利这样做。
Why are these the tribes that hide from man?
为什么这些部落会躲着人？
Here's why.
这是为什么。
Obviously, some of this  was set off in 1492.
很显然，部分是起源于1492年。
But at the turn of the last century was the rubber trade.
但是在上世纪开始出现橡胶贸易。
The demand for natural rubber,
对天然橡胶的需求，
which came from the Amazon,
而天然橡胶来自亚马逊，
set off the botanical equivalent of a gold rush.
促成了植物界的淘金热潮。
Rubber for bicycle tires,
橡胶用于自行车胎，
rubber for automobile tires,
橡胶用于汽车轮胎，
rubber for zeppelins.
橡胶用于齐柏林飞艇。
It was a mad race to get that rubber,
橡胶被人们疯抢，
and the man on the left, Julio Arana,
而左边这个人，朱利奥·阿拉纳，
is one of the true thugs of the story.
是这个故事中最混蛋的恶棍。
His people, his company,
他的人，他的公司，
and other companies like them
还有其他的类似公司，
killed, massacred, tortured, butchered Indians
谋杀，屠杀，虐待，屠宰了Witoto等印第安部落，
like the Witotos you see on the right hand side of the slide.
幻灯片右边就是。
Even today, when people come out of the forest,
即便在今天，当土著部落走出丛林，
the story seldom has a happy ending.
故事也往往没有好的结局。
These are Nukaks. They were contacted in the '80s.
这些是Nukak人。外界80年代时与他们联络。
Within a year, everybody over 40 was dead.
1年之内，40岁以上的都死了。
And remember, these are preliterate societies.
要记得，他们是尚无文字的社会。
The elders are the libraries.
长者就是图书馆。
Every time a shaman dies,
每次一位萨满死去，
it's as if a library has burned down.
就好像一个图书馆被烧毁。
They have been forced off their lands.
他们被逼迫离开自己的土地。
The drug traffickers have taken over the Nukak lands,
毒贩们霸占了Nukak部落的土地。
and the Nukaks live as beggars in public parks in eastern Colombia.
他们在哥伦比亚东部的公园中当起了乞丐。
From the Nukak lands, I want to  take you to the southwest,
从Nukak部落的土地，我带你去西南部，
to the most spectacular  landscape in the world:
来到世界最壮丽的景观：
Chiribiquete National Park.
奇里维克特国家公园。
It was surrounded by three isolated tribes
它四周环绕着三个与世隔绝的部落，
and thanks to the Colombian government and Colombian colleagues,
在哥伦比亚政府和哥伦比亚同僚的努力下，
it has now expanded.
国家公园范围现在扩大了。
It's bigger than the state of Maryland.
它比马里兰州的面积还大。
It is a treasure trove of botanical diversity.
它是植物多样化的宝库。
It was first explored botanically in 1943
奇里维克特山最早在1943年进行了植物学探索，
by my mentor, Richard Schultes,
探索由我的导师，理查德·舒尔特斯进行。
seen here atop the Bell Mountain,
这里看到的是他在贝尔山的顶端，
the sacred mountains of the Karijonas.
贝尔山是Karijona部落的圣山。
And let me show you what it looks like today.
让我带你看看现在那里是什么样。
Flying over Chiribiquete,
飞跃奇里维克特山，
realize that these lost world mountains are still lost.
这些与世隔绝的山仍旧是与世隔绝的。
No scientist has been atop them.
没有科学家登顶过。
In fact, nobody has been atop the Bell Mountain
事实上，自舒尔特斯1943年以来，
since Schultes in '43.
再也没有人登顶过贝尔山。
And we'll end up here with the Bell Mountain
我们前面就是贝尔山，
just to the east of the picture.
就在画面东部。
Let me show you what it looks like today.
让我带你们看看它现在的样子。
Not only is this a treasure trove of botanical diversity,
它不仅仅是植物多样化的宝库，
not only is it home to three isolated tribes,
也不仅仅是三个与世隔绝部落的家园，
but it's the greatest treasure trove of pre-Colombian art in the world:
它还是世界上最伟大的前哥伦布时期的艺术宝库，
over 200,000 paintings.
拥有超过20万幅画作。
The Dutch scientist Thomas van der Hammen
荷兰科学家托马斯·范德哈门
described this as the Sistine Chapel of the Amazon Rainforest.
称其为亚马逊热带雨林的西斯廷圣母院。
But move from Chiribiquete down to the southeast,
从奇里维克特山向东南方去，
again in the Colombian Amazon.
回到哥伦比亚亚马逊。
Remember, the Colombian Amazon is bigger than New England.
请记得，哥伦比亚亚马逊比新英格兰面积还广。
The Amazon's a big forest,
亚马逊是一大片森林，
and Brazil's got a big part of it,
巴西有很大一部分，
but not all of it.
但不是全部。
Moving down to these two national parks,
来到这两个国家公园，
Cahuinari and Puré in the Colombian Amazon —
位于哥伦比亚亚马逊的卡维纳里河国家公园和普伦国家公园 —
that's the Brazilian border to the right —
右边是巴西边境 —
it's home to several groups of isolated and uncontacted peoples.
是许多与世隔绝的部落的家园。
To the trained eye, you can look at the roofs of these malocas, these longhouses,
如果你有能力，你能看出这些是长屋的房顶，
and see that there's cultural diversity.
看出那里的文化多样性。
These are, in fact, different tribes.
这些其实是不同的部落。
As isolated as these areas are,
尽管这些地方如此隔绝，
let me show you how the  outside world is crowding in.
我来给你们看外界是如何进行侵蚀的。
Here we see trade and transport increased in Putumayo.
这里，我们能看到普图马约河的贸易和运输增长。
With the diminishment of the Civil War in Colombia,
随着哥伦比亚内战的结束，
the outside world is showing up.
外界开始侵入。
To the north, we have illegal gold mining,
北边，有非法的金矿，
also from the east, from Brazil.
东边来自巴西的也有。
There's increased hunting and fishing for commercial purposes.
商业目的的狩猎和捕鱼活动也越来越多。
We see illegal logging coming from the south,
南边我们能看到非法采木，
and drug runners are trying to move through the park and get into Brazil.
毒贩子也想穿过国家公园去巴西。
This, in the past, is why you didn't mess with isolated Indians.
这就是为什么在过去，你别惹与世隔绝的印第安人。
And if it looks like this picture is out of focus
如果这张照片看起来有点失焦，
because it was taken in a hurry, here's why.
因为拍摄的时候匆匆忙忙，而这就是为什么。
(Laughter)
（笑声）
This looks like — (Applause)
这看起来像 — （掌声）
This looks like a hangar from the Brazilian Amazon.
这看起来像是在巴西亚马逊的机库。
This is an art exhibit in Havana, Cuba.
这其实是古巴哈瓦那的艺术展，
A group called Los Carpinteros.
创作自一个叫做“Los Carpinteros”的组织。
This is their perception of why you  shouldn't mess with uncontacted Indians.
这是他们想象中的你为什么别惹与世隔绝的的印第安人。
But the world is changing.
但是世界在变化。
These are Mashco-Piros on the Brazil-Peru border
这些是Mashco-Piro人在巴西秘鲁边境，
who stumbled out of the jungle
他们逃出丛林
because they were essentially chased out
因为他们被驱赶出来，
by drug runners and timber people.
被毒贩和采木的人。
And in Peru, there's a very nasty business.
在秘鲁，有个很邪恶的行业
It's called human safaris.
叫人类游猎。
They will take you in to isolated groups to take their picture.
他们带你去隔绝部落照相。
Of course, when you give them  clothes, when you give them tools,
当然，你给他们衣服，给他们工具，
you also give them diseases.
你也带给他们疾病。
We call these "inhuman safaris."
我们管这个叫“反人类游猎”。
These are Indians again  on the Peru border,
这又是印第安人，在秘鲁边境，
who were overflown by flights sponsored by missionaries.
被传教士带着飞到这里。
They want to get in there and turn them into Christians.
传教士想把他们变成基督徒。
We know how that turns out.
我们都知道这样做的结果。
What's to be done?
能做些什么？
Introduce technology to the contacted tribes,
传播科技给已经有联系的部落，
not the uncontacted tribes,
不是隔绝的部落，
in a culturally sensitive way.
并在传播过程中照顾到他们的文化。
This is the perfect marriage of  ancient shamanic wisdom
这是古老的萨满智慧与
and 21st century technology.
21世纪科技的完美联姻。
We've done this now with over 30 tribes,
我们已经跟超过30个部落合作了。
mapped, managed and increased protection of over 70 million acres of ancestral rainforest.
我们测绘了，管理了，并加强保护了超过七千万英亩的古老热带雨林。
(Applause)
（掌声）
So this allows the Indians to take control of their environmental and cultural destiny.
这能让印第安人掌控他们的环境和文化未来。
They also then set up guard houses
他们还设立了岗哨房，
to keep outsiders out.
不让外人进入。
These are Indians, trained as indigenous park rangers,
这些是印第安人，经过受训成为巡山人，
patrolling the borders
在边境巡逻，
and keeping the outside world at bay.
防止外部世界进入。
This is a picture of actual contact.
这是与部落接触时的照片。
These are Chitonahua Indians
他们是Chitonahua印第安部落，
on the Brazil-Peru border.
位于巴西秘鲁边境。
They've come out of the jungle
他们从丛林中走出，
asking for help.
寻求帮助。
They were shot at,
他们遭到枪击，
their malocas, their  longhouses, were burned.
他们的长屋被焚毁。
Some of them were massacred.
他们有的人被屠杀。
Using automatic weapons to  slaughter uncontacted peoples
使用自动化武器对付这些与世隔绝的部落
is the single most despicable and  disgusting human rights abuse
是我们地球上如今最可耻最可恶的
on our planet today, and it has to stop.
反人类行径，这一行径必须停止。
(Applause)
（掌声）
But let me conclude by saying,
在结尾，请让我说，
this work can be spiritually rewarding,
这一工作对心灵是很有好处的，
but it's difficult and it can be dangerous.
但也是困难的，还会是很危险的。
Two colleagues of mine passed away recently
我的两个同事最近刚刚去世，
in the crash of a small plane.
死于小型飞机坠毁。
They were serving the forest
他们在保护森林，
to protect those uncontacted tribes.
保卫这些隔绝的部落。
So the question is, in conclusion,
那么在结尾，问题是，
is what the future holds.
未来会怎么样。
These are the Uray people in Brazil.
这些是巴西的Uray部落。
What does the future hold for them,
他们的未来会怎样。
and what does the future hold for us?
我们的未来会怎样？
Let's think differently.
让我们换个想法。
Let's make a better world.
让我们一起建立一个更好的世界。
If the climate's going to change,
如果气候变化一定要发生，
let's have a climate that changes for the better rather than the worse.
那就让气候变好，而不是变坏。
Let's live on a planet
让我们所生活的星球上
full of luxuriant vegetation,
充满丰富的植被，
in which isolated peoples
而隔绝的部落
can remain in isolation,
能够保持隔绝，
can maintain that mystery
能够继续那份神秘，
and that knowledge
还有那些智慧，
if they so choose.
如果他们愿意这样。
Let's live in a world
让我们所生活的世界里，
where the shamans live in these forests
萨满生活在树林中，
and heal themselves and us
用他们神秘的植物
with their mystical plants
和神圣的猴蛙，
and their sacred frogs.
治疗他们，还有我们。
Thanks again.
谢谢。
(Applause)
（掌声）